DR. IOANA-ELENA OANA

Research Fellow European University Institute

Google Scholar citations: 292, h-index = 8, i10-index = 8

◆ Badia Fiesolana - BF260, Via dei Roccettini 9, 50014, Fiesole, Italy

■ ioana.oana@eui.eu ◇ 🏠 https://nenaoana.github.io

I am a political scientist currently working as a Research Fellow at the European University Institute (EUI) within the framework of the SOLID project led by Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi, Prof. Maurizio Ferrera, and Prof. Waltraud Schelkle. Before my current position, I completed my PhD in Comparative Politics with an additional specialization in Research Methodology at Central European University (CEU) in April, 2019. My research agenda focuses on crisis politics and policies, political behavior and public opinion formation, and social movements and protest. My work concentrates on the interaction between the supply and demand side of politics within the multiple crises that have hit European countries and the EU since 2008, with much of my ongoing publication projects inquiring into political dynamics spurred by the invasion of Ukraine. Beyond these substantive interests, I also focus on research methodology with a pluralist outlook and R software development. I work with text-as-data techniques for semi-automated protest event analysis, surveys and survey experiments, and I develop analytic protocols and software for qualitative comparative analysis.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Research Fellow 06/2019 - present

SOLID ERC Project (PI: Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi) European University Institute, Florence, Italy

Research Fellow 02/2019 - 06/2019

POLCON ERC Project (PI: Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi)

European University Institute, Florence, Italy

EDUCATION

PhD in Political Science 09/2013 - 04/2019

Specialization: Comparative Politics and Research Methodology

Central European University, Budapest (Supervisor: Prof. Zsolt Enyedi)

Thesis: Collective Mobilization and Dynamic Representation: From Citizens to Policy and Back Again

MA in Political Science (Distinction)

09/2011 - 09/2013

Specialization: Social Science Methodology

Central European University, Budapest (Supervisor: Prof. Levente Littvay)

Thesis: When does information matter? Complexity, Cognitive Heuristics and Democratic Competence

BA in Political Science (Valedictorian, GPA: 4.00)

09/2008 - 06/2011

Department of Political Science, SNSPA, Bucharest

BA in Communication and Public Relations (Thesis not submitted)

09/2008 - 06/2011

Department of Communication and Public Relations, SNSPA, Bucharest

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE PRIOR TO CURRENT POSITION

POLPART ADVANCED ERC (PI: Prof. Bert Klandermans)

08/2014-11/2018

Research Affiliate

- gathering and analyzing survey, experimental, and focus group data on party and protest participation in Europe;

POLCON ADVANCED ERC (PI: Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi)

04/2017-09/2017

Coder

- coding contentious political events in Romania;

"Experimental Political Behavior" (CEU Research Support Scheme)

01/2013-07/2013

Scheme Beneficiary

(awarded to Prof. Levente Littvay, CEU, Budapest)

- designing and conducting a lab experiment on voting behavior;

Pilot Study "The Post-Socialist Welfare States" (PI: Prof. Julia Szalai) 03/2012-07/2012 Research Assistant

- collecting and analyzing interview data with public servants in Romania;

RESEARCH VISITS

European University Institute, Florence, Italy

01/2017 - 05/2017

Department of Political and Social Sciences (Host Supervisor: Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi)

VU University, Amsterdam, Netherlands

01/2015 - 07/2015

Department of Sociology (Host Supervisor: Prof. Bert Klandermans)

University of Padua, Padua, Italy

09/2009 - 02/2010

Department of Political Science

GRANTS, AWARDS & FUNDING

Marie Skłodowska-Curie Individual Fellowship (€212,933, grant awarded, but deferred/not accepted due to current position) 02/2019

Full CEU Doctoral Fellowship (Tuition: €30,000; Stipend: €25,500)

09/2013-02/2019

ECPR Dirk-Berg Schlosser Award for outstanding pedagogical skills (€500)

08/2018

Marie Skłodowska-Curie Individual Fellowship Seal of Excellence

04/2018

National Science Foundation and Maxwell School Grant for attending IQMR, Maxwell School, Syracuse University, NY, USA (Amount: €300 + accommodation) 06/2017

CEU Summer School Grant for attending the IQMR, Maxwell School, Syracuse University, NY, USA (Amount: ≤ 694)

CEU Doctoral Research Support Grant for a research stay at EUI, Florence (Amount: €4,000) 05/2016

CEU Conference Grant for the ECPR General Conference, Prague (Amount: €448) 06/2016

CEU Departmental Award for Excellence in Master Studies

02/2012

CEU Full Fellowship for Master Students (Tuition: $\leq 24,000$; Stipend: $\leq 6,000 + \text{accommodation}$) 09/2011-06/2013

Valedictorian Award, Department of Political Science, SNSPA, Bucharest

06/2011

"Olympic Merit" Scholarship from the Romanian Government (Amount: €3,500) 09/2008-06/2011

Merit Scholarship from the Department of Political Science, SNSPA, Bucharest (Amount: €2,500) 09/2008-06/2011

METHODS TRAINING

Institute for Qualitative & Multi-Method Research, Maxwell School, Syracuse, USA

<u>Workshops Attended:</u> Automated Text-Analysis; Multi-method research; Natural experiments; Causal inference from causal models; QCA; 06/2017

ECPR Winter School in Methods and Techniques, Bamberg

Workshop Attended: Multi-level modeling

03/2016

Central European University, Budapest

<u>Methods classes attended:</u> Quantitative Methods: Analyzing Countries, Research Methods and Design, Multivariate Statistics, Survey Methodology, Qualitative Research Methods, Set-Theoretic Methods for the Social Sciences, Network Science, Experimental Methods, Mathematical Statistics, Missing Data Problems in Statistical Inference;

2011-2015

SERVICE TO THE PROFESSION

Reviewer for: American Political Science Review, West European Politics, Sociological Methods & Research, Regulation & Governance, Swiss Political Science Review, Regional & Federal Studies, Policy Studies Journal, Quality & Quantity, Social Movement Studies, Compasss Working Paper Series, PLOS ONE

PROGRAMMING AND LANGUAGE SKILLS

Software & Other Tools: R & RStudio, R Markdown & Sweave, LATEX, Python, SPSS, STATA;

Languages: Romanian – native; English – proficient; Italian – proficient;

French – elementary; Spanish – elementary;

REFERENCES

Prof. Hanspeter Kriesi

European University Institute
Department of Political and Social Sciences

➤ hanspeter.kriesi@eui.eu

J [+39] 055 4685 302

Prof. Carsten Q. Schneider Central European University Department of Political Science

✓ schneiderc@ceu.edu

J [+43] 1 25230 3086

Prof. Maurizio Ferrera Universita degli Studi di Milano

Department of Social and Political Sciences

➤ Maurizio.Ferrera@unimi.it

J [+39] 025 0321 176

LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

Books and Special Issues (peer-reviewed)

Ioana-Elena Oana, Stefano Ronchi, and Zbigniew Truchlewski. Forthcoming. "EU polity resilience in times of COVID? Solidarity, legitimacy, and polity maintenance." Special Issue accepted at Comparative European Politics.

Ioana-Elena Oana, Carsten Q. Schneider, and Eva Thomann. 2021. "Qualitative Comparative Analysis using R: A Beginner's Guide." Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Peer-reviewed Articles

Hanspeter Kriesi and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. forthcoming. "Protest in unlikely times: dynamics of collective mobilization in Europe during the COVID-19 crisis". Accepted at Journal of European Public Policy.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Abel Bojar. forthcoming. "Populism, Anti-technocratic Attitudes, and COVID-19 related Conspiracy Beliefs across Europe". Accepted at Comparative European Politics.

Chendi Wang, Abel Bojar, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, and Zbigniew Truchlewski. forthcoming. "Emergency politics, mass sentiment and the EU during COVID." Accepted at Comparative European Politics.

Ioana-Elena Oana, Alessandro Pellegata, and Chendi Wang. 2021. "A cure worse than the disease? Exploring the health-economy trade-off during COVID-19." West European Politics 44(5-6): 1232-1257.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Carsten Q. Schneider. 2021. "A Robustness Test Protocol for Applied QCA: Theory and R Software Application." Sociological Methods & Research. https://doi.org/10.1177/00491241211036158.

Endre Borbath, Sophia Hunger, Swen Hutter and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2021. "Civic and Political Engagement during the Multifaceted COVID-19 Crisis". Swiss Political Science Review 27: 311-324.

Hanspeter Kriesi, Argyrios Altiparmakis, Abel Bojar and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2021. "Debordering and re-bordering in the refugee crisis: a case of 'defensive integration'". Journal of European Public Policy 28(3): 331-349.

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2019. "Party and protest participation patterns among students in new and old democracies." Partecipazione e Conflitto 12(1): 71-111.

Maarten and Bezouw, Anastasia Garyfallou, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, Sebastien Rojon. 2019. "A methodology for cross-national comparative focus group research: illustrations from discussions about political protest." Quality & Quantity 53(6): 2719-2739.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Carsten Schneider. 2018. "SetMethods: an Add-on Package for Advanced QCA." The R Journal 10(1): 507-533.

Marcel Verhoeven and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2017. "Necessary and Sufficient Conditions for Audience Success of Media Product Brands: A field report on a two-step fsQCA with 10 conditions and 255 cases." COMPASSS WP Series 89.

Chapters in Edited Volumes & Other Publications

Ioana-Elena Oana. Qualitative Comparative Analysis. Forthcoming. In Oxford Handbook: Doing Good Qualitative Research. Eds. Jennifer Cyr and Sara Wallace Goodman. In press at Oxford University Press.

Hanspeter Kriesi and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2021. Asylum Policy Preferences Among the European Publics: Confict Configurations at the Transnational and Domestic Level." Robert Schuman Centre for Advanced Studies Research Paper No. RSC 93.

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2019. "Reinvigorating Romania's Civil Society: Talking About Politics and Corruption in Romania.", In When Citizens Talk About Politics. Eds. Clare Saunders and Bert Klandermans. Routledge.

Maarten and Bezouw, Anastasia Garyfallou, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, Sebastien Rojon, Clare Saunders. 2019. "Methodological appendix - Studying political talk using cross-national focus groups." In When Citizens Talk About Politics. Eds. Clare Saunders and Bert Klandermans. Routledge.

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2014. "The economy of dictatorship and democracy." In Economic and Evolutionary Approaches in Social Sciences. Ed. Mihai Ungureanu, Wolters Kluver, pp. 67-86.

Software Packages

Ioana-Elena Oana, Juraj Medzihorsky, Mario Quaranta, Carsten Q. Schneider. 2018. SetMethods: Functions for Set-Theoretic Multi-Method Research and Advanced QCA. R package (about 50,000 CRAN downloads).

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2020. MDScosa: Functions for Multidimensional Scaling of Election Campaign Data. R package.

Engagement & Outreach Publications

Ioana-Elena Oana and Alexandru Moise. 2022. "How unified are Europeans' views on the war in Ukraine?." EUIdeas Blog post.

Alexandru Moise and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2022. "Acceptance of Refugees and Solidarity in the EU." Migration Policy Center Blog post.

Ioana-Elena Oana. 2021. "Covid-19: spur or restraint to citizen engagement?." EUIdeas Blog post.

Hanspeter Kriesi and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. 2021. "Transnational and domestic conflicts in asylum policies: preferences among the European publics." Migration Policy Center Blog post.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Hanspeter Kriesi. 2020. "Report on Coronavirus Survey in Italy: First Two Waves." EUI European Governance and Politics Programme. Online Research Report

Ioana-Elena Oana and Hanspeter Kriesi. 2020. "Report on Coronavirus Survey in Italy: Comparison of First Three Waves." EUI European Governance and Politics Programme. Online Research Report

Thomann, Eva, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, and Stefan Wittwer. 2018. "Performing fuzzy and crisp set QCA with R: A user-oriented beginner's guide."

Work under Review and in Progress

Book manuscripts

Hanspeter Kriesi, Argyrios Altiparmakis, Abel Bojar, and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. "Coming to terms with the refugee crisis in the EU." Manuscript under review at Cambridge University Press.

Hanspeter Kriesi, Alexandru Moise, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, and Zbigniew Truchlewski. "Bonding, Binding, and Bounding: EU Polity Building in the Covid Crisis." Manuscript in progress.

Ioana-Elena Oana. "Collective Mobilization and Dynamic Representation: From Citizens to Policy and Back Again." Manuscript in progress (based on PhD thesis monograph).

Papers in peer review

Ioana-Elena Oana, Alexandru Moise, and Zbigniew Truchlewski. Two-Level Games and European Solidarity for Energy Sanctions: Experimental Evidence from Seven EU Countries.

Ioana-Elena Oana and Zbigniew Truchlewski. Circles of Bonding: Experimental Evidence on Crossnational Solidarity in the EU during the Covid Crisis.

Zbigniew Truchlewski, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, and Alexandru Moise. A fading Rally-around-the-Flag Moment? Bonding and Support for EU integration in the Ukraine Crisis.

Ioana-Elena Oana, Abel Bojar, and Chendi Wang. The COVID-19 lockdown paradox: support for democracy in times of democratic restrictions.

Abel Bojar, Anna Kyriazi, Zbigniew Truchlewski, and **Ioana-Elena Oana**. Policy Process Analysis: an introduction to a novel method.

Papers in progress

Alexandru Moise, **Ioana-Elena Oana**, and Zbigniew Truchlewski. European military capacity after the Russian Invasion of Ukraine: Experimental Evidence from seven EU Countries.

Ioana-Elena Oana. Dynamics of Protest and the Role of Civil Society in the Refugee Crisis.

Ioana-Elena Oana. Policy output legitimacy in the refugee crisis: A survey experiment on the consequences of asylum policy for EU support in Europe.

Chapters in progress

Ioana-Elena Oana and Carsten Q. Schneider. Qualitative Comparative Analysis. In Elgar Concise Encyclopedia of Research Methods in the Social Sciences. Edward Elgal Publishing.

SELECTED CONFERENCE PAPERS & GUEST LECTURES

UOC (Universitat Oberta de Catalunya)

Guest Lecture: Two-Level Games and European Solidarity for Energy Sanctions: Experimental Evidence from Seven EU Countries. SASE - Society for the Advancement of Socio-Economics O7/2022 Circles of Bonding: Experimental Evidence on Cross-national Solidarity in the EU during the Covid Crisis.

scheduled 11/2022

CES - Twenty-Eighth International Conference of Europeanists	07/2022
Populism, Dissatisfaction, and COVID-19 related Conspiracy Beliefs across Europe.	

EUI Migration Policy Center Conference Dynamics of Protest and the Role of Civil Society in the Refugee Crisis.	06/2022
City University London - Political Change Lecture Series Populism, Dissatisfaction, and COVID-19 related Conspiracy Beliefs across Europe.	05/2022

ECPR Conference of the Standing Group on European Union

106/2021

108/2021

109/2021

109/2021

109/2021

109/2021

KU Leuven, Master program in European policies and politics O2/2021 Guest Lecture in Comparative Analysis for Public Policy

Expert Workshop on QCA, Antwerp Management School, Belgium 05/2019Case Orientation and Parameters of Fit Orientation. A Proposal for Systematized Robustness Tests in $QCA \ using \ R$ 11/2018 West University of Timisoara, Romania Guest Lecture on Party and Protest Participation Patterns among Students in New and Old DemocraciesInternational QCA Expert Workshop, ETH Zurich, Switzerland 11/2018 Fit-oriented and Case-oriented Robustness in QCA Exeter Doctoral Conference, University of Exeter, UK 03/2018 How Policy Change affects Alternative Participation - A Vignette Experiment Annual Doctoral Conference, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary 03/2018 The Participation Consequences of Policy Change – A Vignette Experiment ECPR Joint Sessions of Workshops, Nottingham, UK 04/2017 The Policy Consequences of Alternative Participation: Civil Society Events and Governmental Attention to Issues Annual Doctoral Conference, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary The Consequences of Alternative Participation: Civil Society Events and Public Expenditure POLPART ADVANCED ERC Project Midterm Conference, Budapest, Hungary 09/2016 Pseudo-reality and self-defeating rationalizations: Mental frames of Political Participation in Romania and Hungary ECPR General Conference, Prague, Czech Republic 09/2016Income Inequality and Policy Responsiveness Perceptions: A Genetic Matching Approach ECPR General Conference, Prague, Czech Republic 09/2016 Civil Society Events, Media, and Environmental Protection Expenditure in Europe 04/2016 Annual Doctoral Conference, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary Income Inequality and Policy Responsiveness Perceptions: A Genetic Matching Approach Annual Doctoral Conference, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary Movements' Impact, Media, and Policy Outputs: A Fuzzy-Set Analysis of Environmental Events' Effects on Environmental Protection Expenditure in Italy

International Association for Media and Communication Research Annual Conference, Dublin, Ireland 06/2013

Internet as a catalyzer for civic and political involvement

Annual Hungarian Political Science Association Meeting, Cluj-Napoca, Romania 06/2013 When does information matter? Complexity, Cognitive Heuristics and Democratic Competence

Contested Claims on Citizenship in the CEE Post-Socialist Welfare States, CEU, Hungary 06/2012

Immaturity and Shortsightedness: Racialization and the Romanian Welfare State

TE

Graduate & PhD Level courses & workshops	
Institute for Qualitative & Multi-Method Research, Syracuse University, USA Qualitative Comparative Analysis with R	2022
CIVICA network joint course (EUI and CEU) Set-Theoretic Methods and Qualitative Comparative Analysis	
Institute for Qualitative & Multi-Method Research, Syracuse University, USA Qualitative Comparative Analysis with R	2021
$\begin{array}{c} \textbf{IPSA-FLACSO Mexico Summer School - Virtual} \\ \textit{Qualitative Comparative Analysis with } R \end{array}$	
ECPR Virtual Methods School Qualitative Comparative Analysis with R	
ECPR Virtual Methods School Advanced Qualitative Comparative Analysis	
ECPR Virtual Methods School Qualitative Comparative Analysis with R	2020
ECPR Virtual Methods School Advanced Qualitative Comparative Analysis	
ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques Introduction to Case-Based Research	2019
ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques Qualitative Comparative Analysis and Fuzzy-Sets	
ECPR Winter School in Methods and Techniquesy Seasoned Scholar Workshops: Quantitative and Qualitative Methods - Selected Topics	
Antwerp Management School, Belgium Intermediate QCA	
University of Helsinki, Finland $R \ for \ QCA$	
West University, Romania Introduction to QCA in R	2018
Lund University, Sweden Introduction to QCA in R	
ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques Seasoned Scholar Workshops: Qualitative and Multi-Method Research - Selected Topics	
University of Exeter Q-Step Centre, UK Introduction to Qualitative Comparative Analysis	

European University Institute, Italy

 $Qualitative\ Comparative\ Analysis\ (QCA)\ with\ R$

ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques

2013 - 2017

Teaching Assistant for Qualitative Comparative Analysis and Fuzzy-Sets

- 5 times
- included teaching Introduction to R and teaching lab seminars in R

Ioana-Elena Oana

 $Teaching\ Assistant\ for\ Advanced\ Qualitative\ Comparative\ Analysis$

- 4 times
- included teaching Introduction to R and teaching lab seminars in R